吕克・贝松
作品
让・雷诺
加里・奥德曼
娜塔莉・波特曼
丹尼・艾洛
杀   手   里   昂
彼得・艾波               迈克尔・巴达鲁库
埃伦・格林                    弗兰克.塞杰尔
音乐：艾瑞克・塞拉
编剧、导演：吕克・贝松
最近还好吗，里昂？
Allora,come stai，leone?
还不错
Bene
我们谈谈生意
Let's talk business.
这死胖子想抢莫里兹奥的生意
This fat bastard is moving in on Morizio's business.
莫里兹奥这人明白事理
You know Morizio is a reasonable guy.
你也知道…他只想谈谈
He just wants…a little conversation.
可这家伙，他什么也不想听
But this guy，He don't wanna hear about it.
也许他会听你的
Maybe he'll listen to you.
他每周二来城里，周二你有空吗？
He comes to town every Tuesday，Are you free Tuesday?
有，我有空
Yeah，I'm free Tuesday.
见到你很高兴，琼斯先生
Nice to see you again，Mr，Jones.
记住，要干净利落
Remember，Neatness counts.
给你半小时
You got one half hour.
一小时
One hour.
什么事？
What?
我是唐托，在楼下，有人想和你谈谈
It's Tonto，Downstairs，There's a guy wants to talk to you.
他什么样？
What's he look like?
挺严肃的
Serious.
告诉他我马上就下去    他上来了
Tell him I'm coming up.  He's coming up.
有人要上来，挺严肃的
Somebody's coming up，Somebody serious.
米奇，眼睛放大点，我们有伴了
Mickey，Open your eyes，We got company.
有伴了
We got company.
来吧
Come on.
停下
Stop，Man!
去告诉司机，在后门等我
Tell the driver to wait for us out back，And hurry up.
心肝，出事了？     没事，宝贝
Sweetie，What's going on?    Don't worry，Baby.
别担心，家常便饭而已
It's cool，Take a nap.
我的天
Oh，My God.
该死的，把两边出口都堵上了
Those fuckers blocked both the exits.
检查阳台
Check the terrace!
911急救电话      快帮帮我
911 emergency.    I need help.
有人想杀我           别挂电话
Somebody's trying to kill me. Just stay on the line.
请稍等
I'll just be off a moment.
我接通负责人
I'm gonna connect you with an officer.
我是杰佛逊警探，需要帮助吗？
DetectiveJefferson，May I help you?
我过会再打过来
I'll call you back.
冷静点，朋友，我有一箱上好的玻利维亚货
Relax，Man，I got half of Bolivia sitting in them suitcases.
绝对没掺过，拿去吧，都是你的了
Hasn't even been cut yet，Go ahead.，Take it,It's yours.
打这个电话
Dial this number.
迟些再联系，好吗？
I'll talk to you later，Sweetie，Okay?
再见
Bye.
喂？       我是莫里兹奥，记得吗？
Hello?     It's Morizio，Remember me?
听说你回城里了           是……不，也不算是
I see you're back in town.     Yeah……I mean，No
我只呆一天
Just for today.
我能肯定，也是最后一天…
So it's safe to say today's your last day in town…
我不想再见到你那死猪脸
and we'll never see your fat fucking face again.
是的，没错
Yeah，Right.
让我和那个朋友谈谈
Let me speak to our mutual friend.
他想和你谈谈
He wants to talk to you.
一定要让他明白，才放他走
Make sure he understands，And let him go.
你明白了吗？
Do you understand?
说出来       我明白了
So say it.     I understand.
很好
Good.
天啊
Jesus.
和平常一样两盒牛奶？
Two milk as usual?
为何把香烟藏起来？
Why did you hide the cigarette?
这里的人太多管闲事
This building's full of rats.
我不想让老爸知道，我的麻烦够多了
I didn't want my old man to find out，Got enough problems.
怎么回事？
What happened?
骑车不小心摔的
I fell off my bike.
别告诉我爸抽烟的事，好吗？
Don't tell my dad about the cigarette，Okay?
为何你要这样对我们？     我不知道
Why are you doing this to us?     I don't know...
这几天有很多鑫钱纠纷，一定是那小子干的
People got memory problems these days，It must be the sun.
知道那小子什么时候出的    我不知道事情是怎么发生的
Know when to come out of the sun.   I don't know how it happened.
我能怎么样？我只是负责保管
What's my job? I'm just a holder.
我将你交给我的货看管得很好，碰都没碰一下
I hold the stuff you give to me，I don't look at it or touch it.
我甚至不知道如何搞鬼     跟我来
I don't know how to cut it.     Try to follow me.
六月时，我们给你的白粉，纯度是100%
In June，We gave you the dope，It tests 100 percent pure.
到了七月，我们给你的那些白粉，纯度只有90%
Now it's July,We pick up the dope,And it tests 90 percent pure.
六月到七月之间，10%被掺了
Somewhere between June and July，Ten percent turned to cut!
我不知道啊，你给东西我，我帮你保管，我就知道这么多
I don't know，It's none of my business，You give me the stuff，I hold it.
那些我都知道     我只是想帮你…
That's all I know.     I'm trying to help you out here...
但你若死不认帐的话…
but if you're gonna be a hard-ass about it...
那我就去打搅他一下
I gotta disturb him.
他最讨厌在听歌时，别人打搅他
When he's into his music，He hates being disturbed.
我说的都是实话
I'm telling you the truth.
我也希望是，因为他能分辨真假…
I hope so，Because he's got a talent for sniffin' out a lie.
很可怕的
It's scary.
他像有第六感
It's almost like a sixth sense.
你想改变主意呢、还是我去打搅他？
Are you gonna change your tune or I gotta bust into his?
我说的都是实话
I'm telling you the truth.
好吧
All right.
史丹
Stan.
对不起，他说没有吞掉那些白粉
I'm sorry，He said he didn't cut the dope.
当然不是他偷的
Of course he didn't.
帮我个忙
Just do me a favor.
明天前找出是谁干的
Find out who did by tomorrow.
中午之前
Noon.
迈基，等一下
Malky，Wait.
我没有吞你的货…
I didn't cut your shit.
你自己去查吧！
Find out yourself!
你在这干嘛？进屋做功课去！
What are you doin' out here? Get inside and do your homework！
我已经做完了  是吗？那进去帮你姐…
I did it already.  Get inside and help your sister...
收拾该死的屋子！
clean up the goddamn house!
别再抽烟了
And stop smoking cigarettes!
1！
One!
2.深吸一口气
Two. Take a deep breath in.
呼气
Take a deep breath out.
深呼吸                时间到了，该我看了
Take a deep breath. Inhale.Time's up. My turn.
如果转台的话，我打爆你的头
Change the channel，And I'll smash your face.
现在是腿部运动，下蹲
Ready for the legs，And down.
对不起，小宝贝
Sorry，Sweetheart.
收紧，放松
Squeeze，Release.
早上好
Good morning.
你好，宝贝
Hi，Honey.
亲爱的，小声点，妈听得头痛了
Sweetheart，Turn that down，Mama's got a headache.
她不让我换台     她想看那些该死的卡通片
She took my turn.     She wants to watch goddamn cartoons!
该多看健身节目
It wouldn't hurt her to move her ass.
我又没有大屁股
I'm not the one with a fat ass around here.
两次向上
Two and up.
那个整天没事干，只会看卡通片？
Can someone who's doing nothing all day but watching cartoons...
能去买点吃的回来吗？
move a little ass and go get some food?
到腿部运动    有种就再说一次！
Legs. Beautiful.   I dare you to say that again.
麦姬，我有麻烦了.     又不是第一次
Margie，I think I screwed up.     It wouldn't be the first time.
你总有麻烦，对吗？
You always come up with somethin'， Right?
我想我这次做的有点过份了
I think I went too far this time.
你现在就很过份，我上班要迟到了
You're goin'too far right now，I'm gonna be late for work.
今天在家上班吧
How about workin'at home today?
感觉到了吗？对了，收腹
Really feel it.That's it， Stomach in.
1…     现在该我了！
One...     Now it's my turn!
妈的，她要打我！
Shit，She's gonna hit me!
爸爸，她要……      妈的，把门关上
Daddy，She's...      Shit，Shut the goddamn door!
Please don't shoot!
臭婊子
Fuckin' bitch.
- Megatron!
- Firm up the whole body.
When you use the Quadra-Step.
Your thigh muscles...
谁来接电话                   我在忙
Can somebody answer the phone?   I'm busy!
喂？  我是马格莱特老师…
Hello?   This is Marguerite McCallister...
新泽西州斯宾塞中学的校长
headmistress at the Spencer School in Wildwood. NewJersey.
兰多先生或太太在家吗？
Is Mr. Or Mrs. Lando home?
我就是兰多太太
This is she.
兰多太太，你丈夫送玛蒂尔达进校时…
Mrs. Lando，When your husband enrolled Mathilda at Spencer...
告诉我们，她是不良少女
he told us she had "Problems."
但你知道，我们能把不良少女
As you know，We pride ourselves on turning troubled girls...
引入正途…
into healthy.Productive young women.
但她们若不肯上学，我们也无能为力了
But if they are not here，There is very little we can do.
玛蒂尔达未经批准，逃课两周
Mathilda left school without permission nearly two weeks ago.
虽然你丈夫预付了一年学费，但学校守则写得很清楚…
I know your husband paid tuition in advance for a year...
但如果您看一下我们寄给您的校规手册…
but if you will refer to the rules and regulations manual we sent you...
您就知道无正式的理由而长期缺席…
you will see that unless there is a valid excuse for prolonged absence...
所预缴学费不能退回
your tuition will be forfeit.
她死了
She's dead.
叫那小鬼快干活
Tell that fuckin' kid to do a little work around here!
收拾干净，这儿乱得让我心烦
Clean up，I'm tired of this fuckin' mess.
快点！
Hurry up!
Why am I feeling
When things could look black
That nothing
could possibly go wrong
This has been
a most unusual day
Love has made me see things
In a different way
生活是否永远艰辛？ 还是仅仅童年才如此？
Is life always this hard，Or is it just when you're a kid?
总是如此
Always like this.
留着用吧
Keep it.
我去买东西，你要些牛奶吗？
I'm going grocery shopping，You want some milk?
1夸脱还是2夸脱？ 买两盒，对吗？
One quart or two?It's two，Right?
我喜欢暴风前那片刻的宁静…
I like these calm little moments before the storm.
这让我想起贝多芬
It reminds me of Beethoven.
你听见了吗？
Can you hear it?
就像伏在草丛里…
It's like when you put your head to the grass...
你能听到小草在生长
you can hear it growin'.
和昆虫的爬行声…
You can hear the insects.
你喜欢贝多芬吗？     算不上吧
Do you like Beethoven?   Couldn't really say.
我来为你们演奏
I'm gonna play you some.
爸爸
Daddy!
你守在这里
You better stay here.
我们说好是中午的
We said noon.
已经过了一分钟
I've got one minute past.
你不喜欢贝多芬
You don't like Beethoven.
你就错过了很多东西…
You don't know what you're missing.
序曲能令人热血沸腾…
Overtures like that get my juices flowing.
它是如此铿锵有力…
So powerful.
但序曲过后，说真的…
But after his openings，To be honest...
实在他妈的有点闷
he does tend to get a little fucking boring.
所以我停下了
That's why I stopped!
搜查这屋子
Toss the apartment.
你喜欢莫扎特，我也喜欢他
You're a Mozart fan，I love him too.
我也爱听莫扎特
I love Mozart!
你知道，他是奥地利人
He was Austrian，You know.
但这方面的造诣就不怎么样了…
But for this kind of work.He's a little bit light.
我比较爱听震撼些的
So I tend to go for the heavier guys.
酷    你他妈的在干什么？
Cool. Dude. What the fuck are you doing?
闭上你的臭嘴
Man.Keep your bombacut mouth shut.
听听勃拉姆斯的作品，他也不错的
Check out Brahms，He's good too.
你懂个屁音乐？            踢开它
What the fuck do you know about music?Man. Knock it off!
你查过床了吗？       没有
You check the mattress?  Nope.
哇！
Wow.
妈的
Oh! Fuck!
他死了
He's dead.
天啊，看看你都干了些什么
Jesus，Look what you did.
史丹，你没事吧？
Stan，You all right?
你干嘛？
What are you doin'?
他已经死了！    他弄脏了我的西服
He's dead!           But he ruined my suit.
我知道，但他已死了
Yeah. I know.But he's dead.
他现在只是一滩烂肉，算了吧，冷静点
He's a piece of meat，Forget about it，Calm down.
我很冷静
I'm calm.
等在这儿，  好的
Stay there，All right?
班尼、班尼
Benny!
真他妈该死，班尼！是我和史丹
Jesus fuckin' Christ. Benny!It's Malky and Stan!
冷静些，好吗？
Take it easy，All right?
走吧
Come on.
走吧，我们出去抽支烟
Come on，Let's get a cigarette.
班尼，我们出来了
Benny，We're comin' out!
班尼，别开枪
Benny，Don't fire!
进去
Get in there!
该死的班尼
Jesus fuckin' Christ. Benny!
我不该穿新西服       要点火吗？
You wear somethin' new and...Got a light?
冷静点
Take it easy.
发生什么事了？
What's happening out there?
没事，我们是缉毒署的警察
It's all right，Ma'am.D.E.A. Police.
放过这可怜的一家吧
Leave that poor family alone.
没事了，     冷静点           我很冷静！我很冷静！
Everything's all right，Just calm down，I am calm. I'm calm.
何不放过这可怜的一家？
Why don't you leave them alone?
他叫你回屋里去
He said go back inside.
史丹，我们进去吧
Stan，I think it's better if we go inside.
班尼，翻遍厨房也要找到那些白粉
Benny，Turn that kitchen upside down!Find that shit!
血腥威利，看你干了什么？你竟然杀死一个4岁的小孩
Willy Blood，Iook what you did!You killed a 4-year-old kid!
求你开开门
Did you really have to do that?
求求你
Please open the door.
班尼，应该有三个孩子
Benny，There are three kids here.
我想史丹杀的是这个女孩
I think Stan killed this girl.
威利那杂种杀的是这个小男孩…
Willy. That asshole.Shot the little boy.
没见到第三个，快去找她
The third one's missing，Find her.
妈的，有个小女孩逃脱了…
Shit，We missed the little girl. Man.
我要在这栋该死的公寓把她找出来
I'm gonna find the fuckin' super in this goddamn building.
你还没认出我吗？我，铁锁，认识你
Don't you recognize me?Me，Grimlock，Know you!
妈的！
Shit.
在这，我找到了       太好了
Yo!   I found it!    Bingo!
他们找到白粉了   我知道
They found it.     I know.
在这儿
There it is.
警察来了，我们最好快离开
There's cops outside，We better go.
警察来了，我们要走了，你留在这儿
It's the cops outside，We better go，You stay here.
我怎么跟他们讲？
What do I say?
告诉他们…
Tell them...
…我们在执行公务
we were doing our job.
你叫什么？      玛蒂尔达
What's your name?  Mathilda.
很遗憾你父亲死了     就算他们不杀他…
Sorry about your father. If somebody didn't do it...
没准那天我也会杀了他
one day or another.I would have probably done it myself.
你妈妈，她……
Your mother，She...
她不是我亲生母亲
She's not my mother.
我姐整天想减肥，可总不见起色
My sister wanted to lose some weight，Bet she never looked better.
她也不是我亲姐，只是同父异母
She's not even my real sister，Just a half sister.
她不是个好姐姐
Not a good half at that.
既然你受不了他们，那为何要哭呢？
If you couldn't stand them，Why are you crying?
那些人杀了我弟弟
They killed my brother.
他做错了什么？他才4岁…
What the hell did he do?He was four years old.
他不爱哭
He never used to cry.
他只喜欢伴在我身边
He just used to sit next to me and cuddle.
我比那臭母猪更像他妈妈
I was more of a mother to him than that goddamned pig ever was.
那样骂猪可不好，猪通常比人更友善
Don't talk like that about pigs，They're usually nicer than people.
可它们臭气熏天
But they smell like shit.
那倒不是
Not true.
事实上，我厨房里刚好有只猪…
As a matter of fact，Right now I have one in my kitchen...
很干净…
that's very clean...
还很香呢           你厨房里没有猪
and smells very nice，You don't have a pig in your kitchen.
有的
Yes. I do.
我刚刚在那里，并没有看到什么猪
I was just in there，And I didn't see any goddamned pig.
别走开，我去找它
Don't move，I'll get him.
小猪，你在那里？
Piggy. Where are you?
找到你了
There you are.
嘿，玛蒂尔达
Hi，Mathilda.
嘿，小猪
Hi，Piggy.
你今天还好吗？
How are you today?
不是太好
I've seen better days.
你叫什么名字？     里昂
What's your name?     Leon.
挺可爱的
Cute name.
有其他亲人，或者可投靠的地方吗？
You have anyone to go to，Any family anyplace else?
我去拿点牛奶
I'm gonna get some more milk.
天啊
Holy shit.
别碰这些
Don't touch that. Please.
里昂，你干那行的？
leon,What do you do for a living?
清道夫
Cleaner.
你是职业杀手？
You're a hit man?
是的     很好
Yeah      Cool.
你什么人都杀？    不杀女人，不碰小孩子，这是规矩
Do you clean anyone?No women，No kids,That's the rules.
干掉那些杀死我弟弟的坏人
How much would it cost to hire someone to get those dirtbags...
要多少钱？
who killed my brother?
5000元一个人头     哇
Five grand a head.  Wow.
我为你打工…
How about I work for you...
…作为交换，你教我杀人好吗？
and in exchange，You teach me how to clean?
你觉得怎样？
What do you think?
我帮你收拾房间，买东西…
I'll clean your place，I'll do the shopping.
甚至洗衣服…
I'll even wash your clothes.
成交？    不，我不答应
Is it a deal?No，It's not a deal.
你要我怎样？我已经无家可归了
What do you want me to do?I've got no place to go.
你今天经历了一场大难
You've had a rough day today.
睡觉去吧，明天再说 好吗？
Go to sleep，And we'll see tomorrow.
你对我真好，里昂…
You've been really great with me，Leon...
你不总是这样…
and it's not always like that.
对吗？
You know?
晚安
Good night.
睡得好吗？
You sleep well?
不错
Good.
吃完早餐你走吧           去那？
After breakfast you gotta take off.  Where to?
不关我的事
Not my problem.
读吧
Read it.
你不识字？
You don't know how to read.
我正在学，但最近工作忙…
I'm learning，But I've had a lot of work lately...
功课没跟上
so I'm a little behind.
写些什么？
What's it say?
我已经决定好我以后的人生了，做一个职业杀手
I've decided what to do with my life，I wanna be a cleaner.
你想当一个职业杀手？
You wanna be a cleaner.Here.
拿去吧，这是道别礼物，去杀人吧，但是别跟着我
Take it，It's a good-bye gift，Go clean，But not with me.
我独来独往，明白吗？    邦尼和克雷是搭挡
I work alone，Understand?    Bonnie and Clyde didn't work alone.
席马和刘易斯也是搭挡，而他们都是最好的
Thelma and Louise didn't work alone，They were the best.
玛蒂尔达，为何这样对我？
Mathilda，Why are you doing this to me?
我一直对你很好…
I've been nothing but nice to you.
昨天我在门外还救了你一命，就在门外
I saved your life yesterday，Right outside the door.
没错，所以你应该负责…
Right，Now you're responsible for it.
如果你要救我，你必须要救得有意义
If you saved my life，You must've saved it for a good reason.
如果你现在丢下我不管，就跟你昨天没有开门是一样的
If you throw me out now，It's like you never opened your door...
跟让我死在你面前一样
like you let me die right there in front of it.
但你开门救了我，所以……
But you did open it，So...
若你不帮我，我觉得自己今晚就会死
If you don't help me，I'll die tonight. I can feel it.
我不想死
I don't wanna die tonight.
玛蒂尔达，你只是个小女孩
Mathilda，You're just a little girl
不要这么悲观，不过  我想你不适合
Don't take it badly，But I don't think you could do it.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
怎么样？
How's that?
不要再做这种蠢事，否则我打爆你的头
Don't you ever do that again or I'll break your head.
明白吗？   好的
You got that? okay
是我就不会那么做，那不专业
I don't work like that，It's not professional.
这行是有规则的     好的
There is rules.    okay
还有，不要不停地说“好的”！    好的
And stop saying "okay"all the time!  okay
很好
Good.
你不能带这东西住宿
You expect to use that in this hotel?
先生，我必须这么做
Mister，I have to use it...
下个月我要去茱丽亚学院面试…
because I have an audition atJuilliard next month...
而我必须练习
and I have to practice.
好吧，但只准在10点前练习
Okay，But not after 10:00.
我保证
I promise
好吧，我让你们住走廊尽头的房间
All right, I'll put you at the end of the hall...
那样就不会吵着别人了
so that you dongt disturb anyone.
请填写这表格
Fill those out. Please.
爸，我来填好吗？我最喜欢填表了
Daddy,Can I please fill them out?I like to check in to hotels.
谢谢，我很快就填好
Thanks,Pop.I'll bring these back in a minute.
4楼
Fourth floor!
谢谢，先生
Thanks，Mister!
你很幸运  你女儿挺有趣的
You're lucky to have a little girl that's interested in things.
我儿子17岁了，还整天游手好闲
I have a kid. 17，Does nothing all day long.
在我把行李搬上去时 我能把这植物暂时放你这吗？
Can I leave my plant here while I take my stuff upstairs?
当然可以
Of course.
我填了我最讨厌的同学的名字
I'm putting in a name of a girl in my class who makes me sick.
要是出麻烦，由她负担好了
If things get hot，She'll take the heat.
拿去，填好了
There. Finished.
你几岁了？    18
How old are you?Eighteen.
18？   要看我身份证吗？
Eighteen? Want to see my license?
不用，你看起来还要小点
No，You just look a little young.
谢谢
Thanks.
里昂，我希望你教我成为像你一样的人
Leon，I want you to teach me how to be like you.
我想要变得和你一样强壮和机灵
I want to be strong and smart like you.
我知道自己现在还不够强壮…
I know I'm not strong enough yet...
但我可以从最基本的学起，理论知识
but I could learn the basics，The theory.
你觉得怎样？只是理论知识
What do you think?Just the theory.
这我需要，里昂
I need this，Leon.
我需要时间来整理一下我的思绪
I need time to get my head together.
好的，我需要……
Yeah，And I need...
喝的
a drink.
别动，我去买
Dongt move，I'll go get one.
你叫我帮你找这些东西时
When you told me to get this baby out for you...
…我还以为自己听错了
I thought my hearing was going.
我想，里昂是职业杀手，只有新手才用这个
I says to myself， " Leongs a pro，Nobody uses that except beginners."
我想保持状态
I like to stay in shape.
当然，你是最棒的
Sure，Always stay on top of it.
就像我，我必须随时掌握这一行的最新动态
It's like me，I gotta know where everything is all the time.
我从不离开这里，除非逼不得已
I never leave this place，Except to go from here to there.
不要改变，里昂，明白吗？   是的
Change aingt good，Leon，You know?  Yeah.
检查一下
Check it.
确定这玩意儿没问题，我信任你
Make sure it's the right thing,I trust you.
尽量少惹麻烦，你要记住，里昂
One thing's got nothing to do with the other. Remember that.leon.
我会记住
I will.
你先要学会用来福枪…
The rifle is the first weapon you learn how to use...
它可让你远距离击杀目标
because it lets you keep your distance from the client.
但越专业的杀手
The closer you get to being a pro...
会越接近目标…
the closer you can get to the client.
而小刀，是你要学的最后一样武器，懂吗？   明白
The knife，For example.Is the last thing you learn,okay.okay
就位
Position.
到最后一刻才能打开瞄准镜，因为它会反光
Never take it off until the last minute，It reflects light.
它能让对方在一里外就看到你的位置
They can see you coming from a mile away.
要穿深色衣服
And always dress down.
衣服不能比地板明亮，懂吗？   明白
Never brighter than the floor，Okay? Okay.
开始练习，这是最好的学习方法
Let's practice now,It's the best way to learn.
谁是目标？
Who should I hit?
随便吧
Whoever.
我等一下就让你们采访好吗？先等我几分钏，谢谢
I'll be with you in a second.Give me a few minutes，Thank you.
你们都散开，我不想看见你们
You guys get lost，I dongt want to see you.
大家就位了吗？      要自然点
Is everyone in position?This has to look natural.
不杀女人和小孩子，是吗？ 是的
No women. No kids. Right? Right.
那个穿黄衣服的跑步人如何？  好的
Jogger in the yellow and orange?  Okay
保持冷静
Keep calm.
视线别离开目标
Dongt take your eyes off him.
放松
Breathe easy.
看准他的运动
Watch his movement.
设想你和他在一起跑
Pretend you're running with him.
试着感觉他的下一个运动位置
Try to feel his next movement.
深呼吸，准备
Take a deep breath，Hold it.
开枪
Now.
我的上帝啊！
Oh. My God!
我没事，我很好           趴下！子弹从那射来的？
I'm all right，I'm fine.Get down! Where'd that come from?
射得不错吧？
One shot. Not bad. Huh?
是谁在开枪？      我透不过气了！别压着我
Who the hell fired?  I just cangt breathe! Get off me.
现在能实弹演习了吗？
Can we try with real bullets now?
今天不行，收拾行装
Not today，Let's pack up.
就像这样
Like that.
不，谢谢     一定要喝了
No，Thanks.    No discussion.
这一切…
"It seemed...
在苏格拉底看来
to Socrates..."
让我来
I'll do it.
里昂，不能成天工作
Leon，All we do is work.
我们休息一下，玩个游戏吧
We need a break，Let's play a game.
什么游戏？     我发明的游戏
What kind of game?I have this great game.
能帮助你思考和记忆，正是你需要的               好的
It makes you think and helps your memory，It's exactly what you need. Okay.
Like a virgin
Touched for the very first time
是谁？     我不知道
Who is it?   I dongt know.
Happy birthday to you
Happy birthday. Mr. President
我不知道
I dongt know.
小胡子
Moustache.
I'm singing in the rain
Just singing in the rain
金凯利？
What a beaut...Gene Kelly?
对了
Good.
到你了
Your turn now.
好了，清教徒
Okay，Pilgrim.
克林特伊斯特伍德？
Clint Eastwood?
我猜不出，我放弃      约翰韦恩
I dongt know,I give up.  John Wayne.
我刚想说是他，我发誓，真棒
I was just about to say that，I swear，It's amazing.
里昂，你真是才华横溢
Leon，Really brilliant.
了不起
Amazing.
你很喜欢这盆植物吗？     它是我的好朋友
You love your plant. Dongt you? It's my best friend.
永远快乐，从来不烦我
Always happy，No questions.
和我一样 你看看
It's like me. You see.
没有根
No roots.
若你喜欢他，应该把它种在公园里 那它就能落地生根了
If you really love it，You shouldplant it in a park so it can have roots.
若要我长得快，你也应该给我浇水
You should be watering me if you want me to grow.
你说得对
You're right.
等等
Wait!
它们一定得脱离盘子，才会有生机
They gotta be jumping out of the plate，They gotta be alive.
好久不见了，里昂
It's been a long time，Leon.
我很想你
I missed you.
而你也错过了一些好工作       我在训练
And you missed some nice jobs too. Been training.
训练是好事，但别过度了
Training's good，But dongt overdo it.
训练可不能赚钱，里昂
Training dongt pay as good as working，Leon.
托尼…
Tony...
我存在你那里的钱…
all the money I make.That you keep for me...
你等钱用？
You need some money?
不，我只是好奇
Just curious.
我一直在工作
I've been working a long time...
从没用过那些钱
and I havengt done anything with my money.
也许有一天，我要用那笔钱
I thought maybe someday I could use it.
你认识了一个女人
You met a woman.
你要小心女人
You gotta be careful with women.
还记得你刚来这的时候吗？
Remember when you arrived in this country?
我刚带你入行时，你还是个乳臭未干的小鬼
When I took you in. You were still wet behind the fucking ears...
而且你那时为了个女人弄得焦头烂额
and. Already. You were in deep shit because of a woman.
不要忘记，里昂       我希望能忘记
Dongt forget that，Leon.  I wish I could sometimes.
你知道，关于我那笔钱…
You know，About my money...
也许我可以…
Maybe I could give...
拿一点出来
a little...
给别人
to someone.
你知道，是去帮别人
You know，To help out.
这是你的钱，我只是帮你保管，就像银行
It's your money，I'm just holding it for you，Like a bank.
但我比银行更可靠，银行常被打劫
Except better than a bank because banks always get knocked off.
而没人敢打劫我
No one knocks off old Tony.
还有，银行里
Besides，With a bank...
有无数文件要填写
there's always tons of forms and all that shit.
但我这呢？不用看、不用写，全记在我脑子里
But old Tony. Nothing to read.Nothing to write. It's all in his head.
我现在识字了
I know how to read now.
那很好，里昂，很好
That's good，Leon.
你的钱就在这里，需要的话，问我拿好了
Your money's here,Whenever you want it,You just ask me.
拿着，这有1000块           我不需要
Here's a grand，Come on.It's okay. I dongt need it.
拿去吧，玩得开心点，拿着      谢谢
Take it，Have some fun，Go ahead.  Thank you.
好了，现在来谈谈生意
All right，Now let's talk business.
别走开，我去拿资料
Dongt move，I'll go get the file.
Manolo,给我朋友里昂来杯牛奶
Manolo,A glass of milk for my friend Leon here.
听着，玛蒂尔达，你要注意
Listen,Mathilda,You better be careful.
你不可以随便和街上的人说话
You cangt just speak to any guy off the street.
里昂，别紧张，这他妈没什么大不了的
Leon，Get a grip，What's the big fucking deal?
我只在等待的时候跟人要根烟抽烟罢了
I was just smoking a butt while I was waiting.
我要你停止讲脏话
I want you to stop cursing.
你不能总是这样和别人交谈
You cangt talk to people like that all the time.
花点心思，学学怎么好好说话        好的
I want you to make an effort to talk nice.  Okay
我要你戒烟，抽烟危害健康
And I want you to stop smoking，It will kill you.
离那怪人远点，他看起来不是什么好东西
Stay away from him，He looks like a weirdo.
我5分钟后出来，呆在我视线范围之内
I'll be out in five minutes，Stand where I can see you.
里昂，我想我爱上你了
Leon，I think I'm kinda falling in love with you.
这是我的初恋，你知道吗？
It's the first time for me，You know.
你从没谈过恋爱，如何知道什么是爱？
How do you know it's love if you've never been in love before?
我能感觉
'Cause I feel it.
那儿？
Where?
胃部
In my stomach.
暖暖的
It's all warm.
以前我老是胃痛，但现在没有了
I always had a knot there，And now it's gone.
玛蒂尔达，恭喜你胃病好了
Mathilda，I'm glad you dongt have a stomachache anymore.
但这不能代表什么
I dongt think it means anything.
我要迟到了，我讨厌工作时迟到
I'm late for work，I hate being late for work.
你女儿的小提琴练得怎样了？
How's the practicing going?
今天过得可好？小姐      练琴练得闷坏了
How are we today. Miss?   A little sick of practicing.
我懂，但你很乖
I understand.
从不吵到别人
But you're doing all right.
我还没接到任何投诉
I havengt received any complaints.
我在弦上盖上布来减少音量
I put a cloth over the strings to lessen the noise.
真聪明
That's very smart.
不是人人爱听音乐的       我知道
Not everyone loves music.  I know.
你爸究竟是干嘛的？
What does your father do?
他是作曲家     真了不起
He's a composer. That's wonderful.
他其实不是我父亲
Except he's not really my father.
他是我的爱人
He's my lover.
我出去散步
Think I'll go for a walk.
周六晚上你做什么？         共进晚餐好吗？
What are you doing Saturday night?  What about dinner?
嘿，你要去那？    找6楼J室的朋友
Where you going?    Visiting friends at 6J.
去吧，周六怎么样？
Go ahead，What about Saturday?
晚上8点      我不知道
About 8:00?    I dongt know.
你已经有约了？
You got plans?
在这里和你会面？
Meet you here?
我们知道你忙，所以会尽快
We know you're a busy man，We'll make this short.
请你详细地说出当天的情形
If you'll just take us step-by-step through exactly what happened.
那人站在这，取出枪来
The guy was here，He went for his gun.
我们就向他开枪
Bang，We shot him.
那些孩子当时在那？       我不知道
Where exactly were the kids?  I dongt know!
你不认为他们当时应该在学校吗？
They should have been at school，Dongt you think?
你的口供说，你是第一个进入现场
Your statement said you were the first man in.
你没看见孩子吗？       门给砸坏了
Didngt you see any kids?  The door was broken.
发生什么事？  你是否按程序办事？
What happened?   Did you follow the procedure?
我死了个兄弟，你们他妈的要我怎样？
I lost a good man here，What the fuck do you want with me?
要你合作
Cooperation.
我没时间回答你们的狗屁问题
I havengt got time for this Mickey Mouse bullshit!
要我合作，到我办公室来，4602号室
You want cooperation? Come up in my office，Room 4602.
小子，回学校去
Kids should be at school.
喂，那是我的篮球
Come on. That's my ball!
还给我，你要去那？
Give that back，Where you going?
该死！你去那？那是我的球
Damn! Where you going. Man? That's my ball!
跟着那辆蓝色汽车
Follow the blue car.
你想我和它一样，鸣警号、闯红灯？
You want me to blast the music and go through the lights?
不，开慢点
No，Drive slowly.
收下你的车钱，然后闭上你的臭嘴，好吗？
Take the hundred bucks，And shut the fuck up.
我不想和你打  但你必须毫无选择地离开
I do not want to fight you.but you leave me no choice.
好孩子  你的想法真妙!
Boy.you just gave me a great idea!
真的是绝妙的想法！欢迎回到E频道！每日新闻
I mean a big one！Welcome back to E！News Daily...
这里是30分钟最新娱乐动态
our 30-minute look at the latest in entertainment news.
我是Bianca Ferrar
I'm Bianca Ferrar.
送给你的，是礼物
It's for you，A present.
要我打开吗？我打开吧
Do you want me to open it? I'll open it.
你喜欢吗？很漂亮，是吗？
How do you like it? Nice. eh?
麦嘉先生？
Mr. McGuffin?
能和你谈谈吗？
Can I have a word with you?
拿去，这是2万元酬金，对吗？
Here，It's for a contract.Twenty grand. right?
他叫诺曼史丹菲尔德
His name is Norman Stansfield.
在缉毒署4602室，联邦广场26号
and he's in room 4602 in the D.E.A. building，26 Federal Plaza.
我不接受          为何？
I'm not taking it.   Why not?
我干不了        那好
It's too heavy.   Well.
你能把枪借我用一天吗？
Will you rent me your gear for the day?
我从不借出我的枪
I never lend out my gear.
但是…
But...
你可以用你自己的枪
you still have your gun.Use it.
帮我个忙，别向窗外乱射，好吗？
Just do me a favor. Dongt shoot out the window.
你为何要这样对我？
Why are you so mean to me?
你能毫不留情地杀死陌生人…
Wildly killing people you dongt give a shit about...
却不肯帮我报灭门之仇？
but you wongt get the bastards that killed my whole family?
复仇不是好事  相信我
Revenge is not good once you're done. Believe.
最好是忘记         忘记？
It's better to forget.   Forget?
当我看到弟弟尸体旁的粉笔线后
After I've seen the outline of my brother's body on the floor...
你以为我能忘记？
you expect me to forget?
我要杀死那帮狗杂种
I want to kill those sons of bitches.
打爆他们的脑袋
Blow their fucking heads off.
你杀了人以后 一切都会变了
Nothing's the same after you've killed someone.
你的生活就从此改变了
Your life is changed forever.
你的余生都要提心吊胆地过活
You have to sleep with one eye open for the rest of your life.
我不管将来如何，里昂
I dongt give a shit about sleeping，Leon.
我只需要爱…
I want love...
或者死
or death.
就是这样
That's it.
我选择死亡
I want death.
别烦我了，玛蒂尔达，我已厌倦了你的游戏
Get off my case， Mathilda，I'm tired of your games.
这游戏很有趣，里昂
There's this really great game，Leon.
它让人变得和善，让人开始思考
Makes people nicer，Starts them thinking.
这是你喜欢的方式
The kind of game you love.
若我羸了…
If I win...
你一生都要陪着我
you keep me with you...for life.
若你输呢？
And if you lose?
你还是独来独往，一如从前
Go shopping alone，like before.
你输定了，玛蒂尔达
You're gonna lose，Mathilda.
你上满了子弹，我听见了
There's a round in the chamber，I heard it.
那又怎样？
So what?
若我中枪身亡，你会怎样？
What's it to you if I end up with a bullet in the head?
若无其事
Nothing.
我希望你没说谎，里昂
I hope you're not lying，Leon.
我也希望你的内心深处，从来没有爱过我
I really hope that deep down inside there's no love in you.
因为，如果你有…
Because if there is...
那么一点点爱我的话…
just a little bit of love in there for me...
那几分钟后，你会后悔一直没有说出自己的真实感受
I think that in a few minutes you'll regret you never said anything.
我爱你，里昂
I love you，Leon.
我羸了
I win.
我受伤了
I took a hit.
现在我需要个帮手
I need a hand now.
我知道她还小，但她学得很快
I know she's young，but she learns fast.
小孩需要人去培养，对吗？
Kids need to be shaped into something，right?
是的，我是这样说过，但这行有年龄限制的
I know，I taught you that，But aingt there an age limit?
她已经18岁了
She's 18.
是吗？
Really?
托尼，来点喝的好吗？
How about something to drink. Tony?
当然，马奴洛. 倒杯牛奶给里昂
Sure，Manolo. glass of milk for Leon.
纹身不错
Nice tattoo.
马奴洛，2杯牛奶
Manolo，make that two.
干嘛戴帽子？     防止感冒
What's that for?    Cangt afford to catch cold.
首先，找出门链在那
First you find out where the chain is.
虽然看不见，但你能感觉到，这里
You cangt see it，but you can feel it，Here.
我按门铃，你和他说话        说什么？
I'll ring，you start talking.   What do I say?
随便你
Whatever you want.
谁？     你好
Yes?        Hi.
是苏珊
It's Susan.
抱歉，你找错房间了，小姑娘
I'm sorry，You must have the wrong door，little girl.
我不认识什么苏珊
I dongt know any Susan.
往后退点，我什么都看不见
Move back a little，I cangt see anything.
过道里的灯没开
The light's out.
外面一片漆黑
It's all dark out here.
先生，我很害怕      好吧
Mister. I'm scared.    Okay.
你他妈的想干嘛？
What the fuck are you doing?
张开嘴
Open up.
若它离开你的嘴，我就开枪，懂吗？
If it leaves your mouth，I'll pull the trigger，capisce?
没问题了，把嘴挪开
Here's okay，Let it go.
我说:"把嘴挪开"
I said. '' Let it go.''
走，到那边去
Move. Move over.
别紧张……
Easy. Easy.
小心点，你想要我
Careful.You want me--
上吧，轮到你了
Go ahead，Your turn.
救命，求你别打我
Help me.Please dongt beat me.
先生？
Sir?
先生，那些白粉不是我的
Sir. it's not my dope.
先生，看我…
Sir. look I…
往左边一点
A little left. please.
开枪之前
Before-- Ple--
现在，再开一枪，确保目标死亡
Now，the security shot.
不，第二枪要打在胸口上方
No，the second goes higher on the chest.
瞄准心肺的部位
Aim for the heart and lungs.
那里 就是那里，懂吗？
There. Right there.You see?
第一枪让目标失态
The first shot takes him out of order.
第二枪解决他           你们他妈的在干嘛？
The second finishes him off.  What are you fucking doing?
千万别打脸
Never in the face.
若目标无法确认，你就拿不到酬金
If they cangt recognize the client，you dongt get paid.
因为你能随便找个人来作替死鬼
You could take out anybody and said you did the job.
明白了？  明白了，千万别打脸
Got it?    Got it，Never in the face.
好，把枪收起来           他妈的，你们想干嘛？
Now you can put the tools away.What are you fucking doing?
他妈的，你们想干嘛？ 嘿，先生！
What the fuck is going on?  Hey. mister!
该死的
What are you fuckin--
你看 若经常使用消音器…
You see. when you use the silencer a lot...
你要在这里放一块布…
you have to put a piece of cloth here...
因为过热可能走火
because it gets very hot and could burn it inside.
用湿布 最好是黑色的湿布
A damp. black cloth is the best.
你在干嘛？
What you doing?
我们说好不杀妇孺和小孩
We said no women. no kids.
你以为毒品只会杀死瘾君子吗？
Who do you think this is gonna kill.junkies and monkeys?
现在，干净了
Now it's clean.
我们走吧
Let's get out of here.
我想我们不该喝酒
I thought we dongt have the right to drink.
我知道，为你第一次当杀手破个例吧
I know，but we're making an exception for your first time.
既然，我们是在庆祝完成任务…
Well，if we're making exceptions for a job well-done...
那就像电影里一样，吻我一下如何？
how about a kiss，like in the movies?
好吧
Yes.
你想干嘛？
What you doing?
我要吻你     拜托你停下来
I'm going to kiss you.I want you to stop. please.
来吧，只是吻一下
Come on，Just a kiss.
停下，别人在看着我们
Stop，Everyone is watching us.
回位子上坐下
Go sit down.
好好享受
Enjoy.
你不相信我  是吗？      什么事？
You dongt believe me. do you?How's that?
我说爱你的时候          玛蒂尔达，忘记它
When I say I'm in love with you.Mathilda. please drop it.
换个话题，好吗？         好吧，对不起
Just change the subject，okay?Okay，Sorry.
先生，你第一次杀人时多少岁？
So. how old were you when you made your first hit?
19岁
Nineteen.
那我羸了你
Beat you.
你干嘛？       我也不能感冒
What you doing?  Cangt afford to catch a cold.
没有门铃          那敲门吧
There's no doorbell.So knock on the door.
谁？         嗨
Yes?          Hi.
我在找瑞本先生的房间…
I'm looking for Mr. Reubengs apartment...
但走廊一片漆黑，我也迷路了
but it's all dark out here in the hall. and I'm lost.
等一下
Just a second.
还要吗？来啊，让我看看你的真面目
You want more? Come on，Show your fucking face.
你们以为可以轻易干掉我？
You think you're going to get me that easily?
遇到这种情况 就尽快采取一些手段
When it's tough like this. you know it's gonna be ugly.
除非你想整天站在这里听他鬼叫
Better make it quick or else we'll be all day listening to his crap.
杂种! 来啊，让我看看你他妈的脸，笨蛋！
Asshole! Come on,show me your fucking face. faggot!
来啊，小把戏         嘿
Come on，gum trick.   Hey.
嘿，那拉环的把戏怎样？你听说过吗？
What about the ring trick? You know that one?
拉环的把戏？来啊，杂种，我等着，快来啊
Ring trick? Come on，asshole，I'm waiting.
做给我看看混蛋
Show it to me. motherfucker.
这就是拉环的把戏
That's the ring trick.
马里奥，回理发店去，晚点再来
Mario，go back to the barbershop，We'll finish later.
里昂，怎样了？都解决了吗？
Leon，what's up? All done already?
比人更友善，对吗？
Nicer than people，eh?
是我告诉你的
I told you that.
你遇上麻烦了？        没有
You got a problem?       No
拿张椅子  坐下
Get the chair. Sit down.
我在想
I was thinking.
如果，有天我出事了
If something happens to me someday--
嘿，里昂，你不会出事的
Hey，Leon，nothing's gonna happen to you.
你有金刚之躯，你刀枪不入
You're indestructible. Bullets slide off you. You play with 'em.
托尼，我是说我那笔钱
Tony，I thought about my money.
你记得那天和我一起来的小女孩吗？         记得
You remember the girl who came here the other day?   Yes
她叫玛蒂尔达
Her name is Mathilda.
若我遭遇不测…
If anything happens to me...
我要你…
I'd like you...
把我的钱…
to give her...
都给她
my money.
包在我身上，里昂
You can count on me，Leon.
谢谢，托尼
Thank you，Tony.
我出去一下
I wongt be long.
我做错什么了？      没有
Did I do something wrong?    No.
这次是笔大生意
This one is too big.
是的 我只能做小生意，对吧？
Yeah. and I only get the leftovers，is that it?
玛蒂尔达，自从我遇上你之后…
Mathilda，since I met you...
一切都和以前不同了
everything's been different.
我只是想，一个人静一段时间
So I just need some time alone.
你也需要时间成长
You need some time to grow up a little.
我早就成熟了 里昂
I finished growing up. Leon.
现在只有年龄在长
I just get older.
但我恰恰相反，我年纪大了
For me it's the opposite，I'm old enough.
我需要时间变得更成熟
I need time to grow up.
妈的
Shit.
传球，快！
Come on! Hustle!
好球      继续
Good shot.  Come on.
你是新来的？住在5楼，对吗？
You're new. arengt you? Fifth floor. right?
你不能坐在这           真的？为何？
You cangt sit here like that.   Really. why not?
没有免费的午餐，就像停车场
Nothing's free，Like a parking meter.
你停车就要付钱，这是规矩
When you stop. you pay. It's the law.
像在电视上         你说什么？
Only on T.V.        What'd you say?
算了，要多少钱？           10块钱
Forget it，How much is your meter?   Ten dollars...
一个月
a month.
有钱找吗？
Got change?
别担心，我可以先付一年
Dongt worry about it，We'll do ten for twelve.
这是今年的，好吗？
I'll pay now for the rest of the year.
好吧，一年
Okay，a year.
我交了钱  还得忍受你们？           不
Does paying rent here mean I have to put up with you guys?
那就到别的地方去玩
So go play somewhere else.
我要静静地思考
I need to think.
站好，喜欢你的工作吗？
Stand up，Dongt you like your job?
食物
Food.
你要去哪？    送外卖，4602房
Where you going?  Special delivery，room 4602.
签个名
Sign here.
这边
Come here.
周末玩得开心点，姑娘们     谢谢
Have a nice weekend，girls.   Thanks.
我要去洗手间
I'm gonna go to the restroom.
送外卖？
Special delivery?
让我猜猜看
Let me guess.
中国菜？
Chinese?
还是泰国菜？
Thai. maybe?
我知道了
I've got it.
是意大利菜
Italian food.
你叫什么名字，小天使？     玛蒂尔达
What's your name，angel?      Mathilda
小天使，把纸袋放在地上
I want you to put the sack on the floor.
很好
Good.
然后你要告诉我，有关意大利菜的事
Now I want you to tell me everything you know about Italian food.
还有特地为我准备这道菜厨师的名字
Dongt forget the name of the chef who fixed it for me.
没人指使我的，我独自来报仇的
Nobody sent me，I do business for myself.
那么这就是…
So this is something...
私人恩怨，对吗？
personal，is it?
我又干了什么…
What filthy piece of shit...
该死的事情吗？
did I do now?
你杀了我弟弟
You killed my brother.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
你想去陪他？          不
And you wanna join him?
总是这样的
It's always the same thing.
当死亡，让你感到恐惧时…
It's when you start to become really afraid of death...
你才会懂得珍惜生命
that you learn to appreciate life.
你喜欢生命吗？甜心
Do you like life. sweetheart?
喜欢       好极了
That's good.
我为我没有兴趣…
Because I take no pleasure...
去杀一个
in taking a life...
不珍惜生命的人…
if it's from a person who doesngt care about it.
史丹，我到处在找你
Stan，I've been looking all over for you.
楼上楼下都找过了  什么事？我很忙
I checked upstairs--What? I'm busy.
迈基死了
It's Malky. man.He's dead.
迈基正和中国人交易
Malky was making a buy for us from the Chinaman.
但这与中国人无关
But they got nothing to do with it.
他们说，有人闯进来，是个职业杀手
They told me this guy came from the outside. He was a pro.
身手敏捷，神出鬼没
He was fast，He fuckingcame out of nowhere.
两秒钟就干掉了那些中国人
Boom. shoots the Chinaman dead in two seconds.
等等，我是警察
Easy. man.I'm a cop.
他转过身，对迈基说
Then turns around，says something to Malky like--
不杀女人和小孩子
No women. no kids.
我认为是私人恩怨
I think it was something personal.
现在，生死真是反复无常
Death is whimsical today.
血  你听见没？
Blood. do you hear me?
是，我听到了.  史丹，放松点
Yeah，I hear you.  Stan，Just chill out. man.
带她去我办公室好吗？
Would you take her up to my office?
好的
All right.
吓死人了
Jesus fucking Christ.
里昂，我的爱人
''Leon，my love.
我知道杀死我弟弟的人在哪里
I know where to find the guys who killed my brother.
他们的头叫诺曼・史丹，他在缉毒署4602室
Their boss is Norman Stansfiield，He's in the D.E.A. building. room 4602.
我要亲手杀他们
I'm gonna do them myself.
若我出事了，桌上有2万元
If something goes wrong，I left you 20 grand on the table.
那是给你的酬金，杀一个人5000，对吗？
It's for a contract,Five grand a head,right?
解决了这件事，我心里才会舒服
I know I'll feel better after I do this.
我爱你 玛蒂尔达
I love you. Mathilda ''
等我一下，很快就好
Wait,I wongt be long.
这是联邦大楼，门口禁止停车
I cangt in front like this,It's a federal building!
他的反应就如我预料
He's gonna do the same exact thing that I said.
9毫米口径的手枪
A nine ''millie.''
子弹
Bullets.
又一把9毫米手枪
Another nine ''millie.''
你打算用这些枪干嘛？
What'd you plan to do with all these guns?
也许，她想杀光整座大楼的人
Maybe she was planning on taking out the whole building.
妈的！
Holy shit!
这是什么？午餐？
What's this? Lunch.
小心，可能有毒
Careful. Blood.might be poisoned.
不会，吃完了再说
There's no anchovies on this.
你说不会太久，但我等了10分钟
Is that what you call ''I wongt be long''? I been here for ten minutes.
我已经尽快了，开车吧
I did my best.
你喜欢吗？
Do you like it?
喜欢
Yes.
再说一次
So say it.
我喜欢
I like it.
你不渴吗？
Not thirsty?
你知道，女孩子的第一次很重要
You know，a girl's first time is very important.
可能影响她的一生
It determines the rest of her life sexually.
我在姐姐的书上看来的
I read that once in one of my sister's magazines.
我朋友们说，她们讨厌第一次性体验
My girlfriends told me they hated their first experience.
那是因为，她们并不喜欢对方
That's because they didngt love the guys.
她们做爱是为了炫耀
They just did it to show off.
然后 她们开始喜欢做爱，就像抽烟一样
Afterwards. they started liking it，like cigarettes.
我的第一次会满意吗？
Will I like it the first time?
玛蒂尔达，不
Mathilda，no.
为什么？
Why not?
我不能
I just cangt.
你爱着别人？       不
You love someone else?  No.
我的意思是
I mean--
很久以前我爱过一个人
There was someone a long time ago.
那时我还没有来美国
Before I came to the States.
她父亲不准她见我
Her father didngt want her to see me.
她出身高贵的家庭
She was from a very respectable family.
而我…
Mine was...
你知道…
you know...
出身贫寒
not so respectable.
所以每次她来见我，她爸就会发怒
Her dad went nuts every time she'd take off to see me.
她仍然偷偷来见你，对吗？
She still snuck off to see you，right?
对
Right.
看，爱情是无法阻挡的，里昂
See，nothing can stop love，Leon.
他杀了她
He killed her.
一枪击中她头部
One shot through the head.
他在监狱呆了两天，就放出来了
They kept him in jail for two days，and they let him go free.
他们说这是意外
They said it was an accident.
所以…
So...
一天晚上…
one night I...
我等着他
waited for him.
带着狙击枪，在500英尺的距离
Five hundred feet with a lens.
他也遇上了"意外"
He also had an accident.
那晚我坐船来到这里…
The same night I took a boat and came here...
见到了我父亲，他为托尼工作
to meet up with my father who was working for Tony.
那时我19岁
I was 19.
从此以后，我再也没有离开过这座城市，而且…
Since then I've never left the city，and...
我也没有再交女朋友
I've never had another girlfriend.
你看，玛蒂尔达…
You see，Mathilda...
我不是一个好情人
I wouldngt be a good lover.
好吧
Okay.
你能帮我个忙吗？
Would you do me one favor?
什么？
What?
我讨厌你睡在沙发上
I'm sick of watching you
sleep on your chair.
我们要同床共枕
We're gonna share the bed.
这不认为这是个好主意
I dongt think it's a good idea.
好了
It's okay.
把腿放在床上
Put your legs up on the bed.
对，很好
Yeah，That's nice.
把头放低，好的，放松
Put your head down，It's okay，Relax.
晚安，里昂
Good night，Leon.
晚安
Good night.
先给我块蛋糕
I want a piece of cake first!
马奴洛，带孩子们去厨房
Manolo，take the kids in the kitchen.
我一直很尊敬你，托尼
I have a lot of respect for your business，Tony.
你过去帮我们杀人…
When you've killed for us in the past...
我们很满意
we've always been satisfied.
但今天发生的事让我为难
That's exactly why today is going to be very hard for me.
希望你谅解我的心情
I hope you'll excuse my mood.
我的人，在你的地盘被杀
My man was killed right here on your turf.
中国人说那杀手…
The Chinks tell me that the hit man...
像是意大利人
was kind of the Italian type.
所以我们想 托尼可能知道些什么
So we figured that Tony might know something.
等等，下面要说的
Wait，There's more.
也许你会感兴趣
You're gonna love this.
几小时后，一个12岁的小女孩走进我办公室…
A few hours later，a little 1 2-year-old girl comes into my office...
武装到牙齿，抱着必死的决心要把我关进停尸间
armed to the teeth. with the firm intention of sending me to the morgue.
你知道是谁把她救走吗？
Do you know who came and got her right there in my building?
就是这个…
The very same...
意大利杀手
Italian hit man.
我很想和他见面
I'm dying to meet him.
放松点，一切都很好，睡得好吗？
Relax，Everything's fine，Sleep well?
我很少睡得好，永远睁着一只眼睡觉
I never really sleep，Got one eye open always.
噢，我忘了
Yeah，I forgot.
我从没见过有人睁着眼睛睡觉、还打鼾呢
I never saw someone with one eye open snore so much.
我打鼾吗？    就像个婴儿
I snore?     Like a baby.
我去买点牛奶作早餐，很快就回来
I'm gonna get some milk for breakfast，I wongt be long.
回来记得敲暗号
Dongt forget the code when you come back.
两下、一下、再两下，对吗？
Two knocks、then one、and two knocks again，Right?
对
Right.
这些先放这里，我还要买点牛奶
Ring these up，I'm gonna go get some milk.
从现在起，不准出声
From here on out，you dongt make a sound.
你点头或摇头来回答我的问题，懂吗？
You answer my questions by nodding yes or shaking your head no.
他独自一人？
Is he alone?
他在等你回去？
Does he expect you?
你有房间的钥匙吗？
Do you have keys to the apartment?
有敲门的暗号吗 让他知道是你？
Is there a code. a way of knocking.so he knows it's you?
A队，准备行动
Alpha team.
收到  准备行动           小心
Final position. We're ready to go.Be careful.
怎么了？ 快！  混蛋
What up? Move! Fuck.
妈的
Shit.
A队，有人死了
Alpha team，Man down.
我警告过你们的
I told you.
把所有人都叫来  “所有人”指什么？
Bring me everyone. What do you mean，''everyone''?
所有的人！
Everyone!
拿着
Take this.
上前看看
Go take a look.
不准动     你看到什么？
Dongt move.  Do you see anything?
是那个家伙，他在这，正用枪指着我的头
It's the guy，He's here，He's got a gun to my head.
不要轻举妄动
Nobody moves.
把女孩放了     冷静一点，朋友
Let the girl go. Take it easy，man!
好的，女孩过来了放了她
Okay，the girl's coming out.Let the girl go.
把墙上的斧头拿下来，就在那，快去
Grab the axe off the wall，Over there，Go!
跟我走
You're coming with us.
妈的，他杀了人质
Christ，he shot him!
杂种！
Bastard!
散开、散开、散开
Move!
把水龙头关上       知道了
Shut the fucking water off!  Got it.
走
Come!
我们处境不妙，请求支援
We're in a bad way here，Send the cats.
我不知道发生了什么事，他们从天而降，我发誓
I dongt know what happened，I didngt see 'em coming，I swear!
我购物后回来，这里到处都是他们的人
I just went shopping and I came back，and they were everywhere.
离窗口远点
Stay away from the window.
来这
Come here.
狙击手
Snipers.
好了，现在把那畜生赶出来
Okay. now. get this fucking asshole out of there.
我们现在怎么出去？          交给我吧，我们要退房了
How are we gonna get outta here now?Leave it to me，We're checking out.
但是这对你来说太窄了，我才勉强能挤进去
But it's not big enough for you，It's barely big enough for me.
我说过没得商量   不，我不走
We said no discussion.  No，I'm not letting--
我不走！我不走！     仔细听好
I'm not going! I wongt go!  Listen to me.
我们在一起是逃不了的，若只有我一个人，我就能办到
We have no chance together，But if I'm alone. I can do it.
相信我，我是专业的
Trust me，I'm in good shape.
我在托尼那有许多钱
I know I've got a lot of money with Tony.
晚点我们拿了钱一起离开这里   就我们两个  好吗？
We'll take it and leave together.just the two of us.Okay?
走吧
Go.
不  你这样说是为了安慰我
You're saying that so I wongt worry.
我不想失去你      你不会失去我的
I dongt wanna lose you.  You're not gonna lose me.
你让我体会了人生的乐趣
You've given me a taste for life.
我很快乐，也想安枕无忧，我有根了
I wanna be happy，sleep in a bed，have roots.
你不会再次孤独的   玛蒂尔达
You'll never be alone again.  Mathilda.
求求你，快走，宝贝，走吧
Please，go now，baby，Go.
冷静点，快走，
Calm down，Go now，Go.
我处理完之后就去托尼那找你 1小时后在托尼处见面
See you at Tony's. I'm gonna clean them all. Tony's in an hour.
我爱你，玛蒂尔达
I love you，Mathilda.
我也爱你，里昂
I love you too，Leon.
嘿，上面怎么了？ 我叫你们抓人，不是拆楼
Hey，what is going on up there? Take the guy out，not the building.
嘿，有人还活着
We've got one breathing here!
叫医护人员来
Get a medic on the horn!
让开路，让他过去
Clear the hall!Let him through!
有人受伤了，让开路，要下楼梯了
We've got a wounded man，Make way! Down those stairs.
走吧、走吧
Let's go! Move!
把他带下楼梯
Get that guy off the stairs!
带你那队回原位去       我找到他了！
Get your team back out there!   I got him!
有两人走楼梯下来了，快点
We've got two men coming down the stairs，Let's hurry!
你没事吧？嘿，我这里需要医生！
You okay? Hey，I need a medic over here!
把屁股移开
Move your fucking asses.
第1组，公寓里情况如何？
Squad Number One，what's the status on the apartment?
什么都看不见，烟太浓了，给我们5分钟
Cangt see shit，Too much smoke，Give us five minutes.
好的，我知道了
You got it.
什么？200人也抓不到一男一女？
What? Two hundred men cangt find one man and a girl?
找到那女孩没有？
Did you find the girl?
你感觉如何？摘下面罩，快
How are you doing? Take your mask off. quick.
让我看看，这个伤口很深
Let me see you. That's deep.Right. And this one here--
你是第3分局的？           对
You're from the 3rd Precinct?
打开他袖口
Let's open up his sleeve a little bit.
好了，没事了，把手放下
All right. fine. Put it down.This one.
你等两分钟，我很快回来
You stay there for two minutes，I'll be right back.
我要戴回面罩，这样容易呼吸
Let me put the mask back on，I breathe better with it.
好的，没事的，坐好别动
You're all right，Sit tight.
好了，所有人都出去，走、走
Come on. everybody out! Let's go! Out!
让开道
Clear the way. men.
你在这干嘛？快走开
What are you doing here? Get out. Come on.
史丹？
Stan?
静候差遣
At your service.
这是   来自
This is from...
玛蒂尔达…
Mathilda…
妈的
Shit.
快从这里出去！
Get out of here!
里昂让我帮你…
Leon asked me to help you out...
若他出事的话 我想他出事了对吗？
if something happened，and I think something happened.
他留下一点钱给你
He put aside a little cash for you.
所以我建议…
So what I'm suggesting is that...
因为你还小…
seeing as how you're still so young...
钱我帮你保管，到你长大为止
I should hold the money for you until you're older.
就像银行，你知道，除…
Like a bank，you know，except...
但我比银行更好，因为银行会被打劫
it's better than a bank'cause banks always get knocked off.
而没人敢打劫托尼
No one knocks off old Tony.
这是你的钱，在这段期间…
But it's your money，In the meantime...
你可以时不时来一趟
all you gotta do is come here every once in awhile...
然后我就给你一点钱拿去花，好吗？…
and I'll dish it out so you can have a little fun.
这里
Here.
先拿100块去花吧        不能给我份工作吗？
Here's a hundred bucks to start. Cangt I get a job instead?
工作？你能干什么？
Ajob? What the hell can you do?
我能杀人
I can clean.
我没有适合12岁小孩的工作
I aingt got no work for a 1 2-year-old kid...
不要再妄想了…
so get it out of your goddamn head!
结束了，游戏结束了
It's over! The game's over!
里昂已经死了
Leongs dead!
你明白吗？
You hear me?
好了，你以为我不伤心吗？
Come on，You think I aingt hurting too?
但他死了
But he's dead.
你必须把这疯狂的一切忘掉，然后回学校去吧
You're gonna forget all this craziness and get your little ass back to school.
拿着钱，离开这里
Now take this money and get the hell outta here.
下个月之前不要让我看你的脸…
Dongt let me see your face till next month...
因为我有名的好脾气已经快被你耗尽了
'cause something tells me I'm about to lose my famous kind streak.
我的父母…
My parents...
都死了…
died...
4周前，死于一场车祸…
in a car accident four weeks ago.
太可怕了
It was terrible.
你刚来时，我们没时间了解对方…
We didngt have the time to get to know one another when you first came here...
但我要你明白，我从不放弃挽救孩子…
but I want you to know I'm not the kind of woman who'd let down a child...
无论她出什么事，无论她犯什么错
whatever her situation，whatever her mistake.
我会尽力帮你的，欢迎你回来
So I'm going to help you and do my best to welcome you here again.
但有个条件:
But on one condition:
你不能再对我说谎了，玛蒂尔达
You have to stop lying to me，Mathilda.
我希望你能信任我…
I want you to take a chance...
相信我
and trust me.
告诉我究竟发生了什么事？
Tell me what happened to you.
我的父母因为毒品案…
My family got shot down by D.E.A. officers...
被缉毒署的人杀了
because of a drug problem.
我遇上了最好的人
I left with the greatest guy on Earth.
他还是最棒的杀手，但他今早死了
He was a hit man. the best in town,but he died this morning.
你不帮我的话，今晚我也会死的
If you dongt help me,I'll be dead by tonight.
你们认识她吗？ 不认识
You know her?  I've never seen her.
我想，我们会在这里好好地生活
I think we'll be okay here.
∮∮他把玩纸牌当作一种自我冥想     毫无疑问他是个出色的牌手∮
∮∮He deals the cards as a meditation     And those he plays never suspect∮
∮他从来不为金钱去玩纸牌，但他总能够赢   他也不是为了赢得尊敬或者荣誉∮
∮He doesn't play for the money he wins   He doesn't play for respect∮
∮他只是为了找到一个答案   为了找到自己心的形状∮
∮He deals the cards to find the answer   The sacred geometry of chance∮
∮一个未知结果隐藏的运算法则   纸牌上的数字跳起了舞∮
∮The hidden law of a probable outcome   The numbers lead a dance∮
∮我知道黑桃是战士手上的剑∮
∮I know that the spades are the swords of a soldier∮
∮我知道梅花是战争的武器∮
∮I know that the clubs are weapons of war∮
∮我还知道在这纸牌艺术里方块意味着赢得金钱∮
∮I know that diamonds mean money for this art∮
∮但这都不是我的 心 的 形状∮
∮But that's not the shape of my heart∮
∮他手中握着一张“方块J”   在后面压着一张“黑桃Q”∮
∮He may play the jack of diamonds   He may lay the queen of spades∮
∮他最后还藏着一张“老K”   但这些记忆正在渐渐淡去∮
∮He may conceal a king in his hand   While the memory of it fades∮
∮我知道黑桃是战士手上的剑∮
∮I know that the spades are the swords of a soldier∮
∮我知道梅花是战争的武器∮
∮I know that the clubs are weapons of war∮
∮我还知道在这纸牌艺术里方块意味着赢得金钱∮
∮I know that diamonds mean money for this art∮
∮但这都不是我的 心 的 形状∮
∮That's not the shape of my heart∮
∮如果我告诉你我爱你∮
∮And if I told you that I loved you∮
∮你可能以为哪里出了错∮
∮You'd maybe think there's something wrong∮
∮其实我并不是一个多面人   我的面具只有一个∮
∮I'm not a man of too many faces   The mask I wear is one∮
∮那些说话的人什么也不知道   要想知道就要付出代价∮
∮Those who speak know nothing   And find out to their cost∮
∮例如在许多地方他们的运气会受到诅咒∮
∮Like those who curse their luck in too many places∮
∮那些害怕的人也会失败∮
∮And those who fear are lost∮
∮我知道黑桃是战士手上的剑∮
∮I know that the spades are the swords of a soldier∮
∮我知道梅花是战争的武器∮
∮I know that the clubs are weapons of war∮
∮我还知道在这纸牌艺术里方块意味着赢得金钱∮
∮I know that diamonds mean money for this art∮
∮但这都不是我 心 的 形状∮
∮But that's not the shape of my heart∮
∮但这都不是我 心 的 形状∮∮
∮That's not the shape of my heart∮∮